Guide to the Evans Family Papers, 1926-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Evans Family papers 1926-1989
Evans family
18 linear feet Extent: 5609 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00369
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Evans Family papers were a gift to Duke University in 1986 and 1989.
Biographical Note
Papers of the Evans Family, active in Durham, N.C. civic leadership, local and national religious leadership, and national journalism.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, albums, clippings, addresses, writings, and other materials that concern the personal lives and careers of the Evans family, particularly Emanuel J. and Sara Evans, their sons, Eli and Robert, and Emanuel's brother, Monroe. The family owned and operated United Department Stores, and for twelve years, 1951 to 1963, Emanuel Evans was mayor of Durham, NC. He was also very active in his synagogue, was a president of VISTAS, and participated actively in the University of North Carolina's Alumni Association. There are two scrapbooks on Emanuel Evans's mayoral terms and a similar volume and other materials devoted to Mrs. Evans's activities as leader of Hadassah including items pertaining to Israel. Mr. Evans's mayoral correspondence is divided into a general file and a subject file. In pictures and personal correspondence, the Nachamson family is often represented. One early clipping from a Fayetteville, N.C. newspaper, tells of Mr. Evans's sister being refused teaching positions because of her Jewish faith. Eli Evans is a correspondent and writer, led the establishment of the National Jewish Archives of Broadcasting, and was on the staff of the Carnegie Foundation that helped launch "Sesame Street." He was president of the UNC student body and a number of items in the collection concern his presidency. Also included is an address of Eli Evans presented during the conference on Southern-Jewish history in 1976, Eli Evans's vita, his unpublished diary of the Kissinger shuttle, and a large number of his writings, many concerning U.S. politics, minorities, and Jews in the South. There is a reprint of a chapter from his book, The Provincials, and reports from the Charles H. Revson Foundation, of which he is president. Also included are materials concerning Eli's brother Robert, a correspondent with CBS, who continued on as a television executive. Their uncle, Monroe Evans, was mayor of Fayetteville, NC, and his service is documented in several of the collection's scrapbooks. One entire scrapbook is devoted to the writings of Mildred and Madeline Evans, Monroe's wife and daughter.
Subject Headings
Evans, Emanuel J.; Evans, Sara Nachamson, 1905-1986; Evans, Robert; Evans, Eli N.; Evans, Monroe; Nachamson family; Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America; University of North Carolina -- Alumni; Charles H. Revson Foundation; Antisemitism; Jews in the Southern States; Department stores; Department stores -- North Carolina; Display of merchandise; United States -- Politics and government; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Israel; Photographs
Detailed Desription of Collection
- Evans Family Series
  - Addresses and Writings, 1946-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Alumni Annual Giving (Box 1)
  - Biographical information, 1953-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Business correspondence, 1937-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Civic Honor Award of the Durham Chamber of Commerce, Evans, E. J. (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1926-1951 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1952-1977, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Committee of One Hundred (Chamber of Commerce) (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1958., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1976, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1977, undated (Box 4)
  - Evans, E. J. "Father of the Year," 1965 (Box 4)
  - Evans, Sara, Obituaries, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Durham Federation of Jewish Charities (Box 4)
  - Hadassah, 1954-1977, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Judaic Studies Program, Duke University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1972-1977, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellany, 1929-1976, undated (Box 5)
  - Pictures:
    - E. J. Evans, 1917-1973, undated (Box 5)
    - E. J. Evans as Mayor of Durham, 1951-1959 (Box 5)
    - E. J. Evans as Mayor of Durham, 1960-1966, undated (Box 5)
    - Sara N. Evans, 1928-1972, undated (Box 5)
    - Robert M. and Eli N. Evans, 1950-1974, undated (Box 5)
    - Evans Family, 1940-1976, undated (Box 5)
    - Nachamson family, 1901-1970, undated (Box 5)
  - Pictures: (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1934-1953 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1953-1977, undated (Box 6)
  - Preferred Stock Certificates (4 vols.) (Box 6)
  - President of the Student Body at the University of North Carolina, Evans, Eli N. (Box 7)
  - Printed material, 1928-1977, undated (Box 7)
  - Printed material, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Synagogue Center/Percival Goodman (Box 7)
  - Suspense file, 1949-1962 (Box 7)
  - United Fund (Box 7)
  - United Jewish Appeal, 1957-1966 (Box 7)
  - University of North Carolina (Box 7)
  - Vistas, Inc.: President's file, 1960-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Watts Hospital (Box 8)
  - Watts Hospital Bond Speakers (Box 8)
  - Oversize materials (Box Sec. A OV5)
- E. J. Evans, Mayor's Office Series
  - Airport, 1952-1961 (Box 9)
  - Appointment for committees, etc. (Box 9)
  - Annual Report (Box 9)
  - Aull, Jr., George H. (City Manager, Durham, N.C.) (Box 9)
  - Centennial (Box 9)
  - Change and improvements, 1953-1961 (Box 9)
  - Complaints and suggestions from individuals (Box 9)
  - "Congratulations for Mayor," 1951, Mar-1961, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence (general), 1951-1953, (7 folders) (Box 10)
  - Correspondence (general), 1954-1963, undated, (7 folders) (Box 11)
  - Correspondence (personal) 1951-1963, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - "Fluoride" (Box 12)
  - Housing Authority (Box 12)
  - Human Relations Committee (Box 12)
  - Lerner, Connie: Miss North Carolina, 1971 (Box 12)
  - Long Range Planning Committee (Chamber of Commerce) (Box 12)
  - Mayor's campaigns, 1951-1963 ( 2 folders) (Box 13)
  - N.C. League of Municipalities, 1951-1961, undated (Box 13)
  - Office of Emergency Planning (Civil Defense Advisory Council) (Box 13)
  - Radio/Television Stations (Box 13)
  - Special Invitations To and From the Mayor, 1958-1950 (Box 13)
  - Speech material (Box 13)
  - "Thank You" letters (Box 13)
  - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 13)
- Eli N. Evans Series:
  - Addresses and Writings of Eli N. Evans: (Box 14)
  - Diary of the Kissinger Shuttle, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Addresses and writings of others (Box 14)
  - Biography (Box 14)
  - Charles H. Revson Foundation, 1978-1986 (Box 14)
  - Pictures (Box 14)
  - The Provincials: A Personal History of Jews in the South by Eli N. Evans (Box 14)
- Scrapbook Series
  - Evans Family, Pictures, ca. 1922-1947 (Box 15)
  - Eli N. Evans, Pictures, High School and UNC (Box 15)
  - Evans Family, "Special Events," 1928-1977 (Box 16)
  - Sara N. Evans, "This is My Life," 1954-1962 (Box 16)
  - E. J. Evans, 1936-1976 (Box 17)
  - Robert M. Evans, 1920-1977 (Box 17)
  - Sara N. Evans, "Eight Sisters in Israel, November - December 1968" (Box 17)
  - Eli N. Evans, Student Body President, UNC, 1957-1958 (Box 18)
  - E. J. Evans, "Retiring Mayor, Durham, NC," 1963 (Box 18)
  - Evans Family, "Publicity," 1928-1955 (Box 18)
  - Evans Family, Pictures, 1948-1976 (Box 19)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral September 1966-March 1967" (Box 19)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral July 1965-September 1966" (Box 20)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral March 1965-June 1965" (Box 20)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "March 1967-April 1969" (Box 21)
  - Monroe E. Evans, 1921-1959 (Box 22)
  - Monroe E. Evans, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "United Service Fund, 1957-1972" (Box 23)
  - Madeline and Mildred Evans, "Writings," 1958-1963 (Box 23)